Guide to the Duke Chapel Records, 1920-[ongoing] UA.17.01.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Chapel records
1920-[ongoing]
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Chapel
UA.17.01.0001
47 Linear Feet
0.23 Gigabytes
Collection contains records relating to the operations and activities of Duke Chapel and ranges in date from 1920-[ongoing]. Material includes administrative records, printed exercise programs and bulletins, transcripts of sermons, oversize material including marriage and baptismal registries, carillon and carillonneur material, miscellaneous clippings, press releases, and published material relating to Duke University and the Chapel. University Archives staff must be consulted in order to determine what material is covered by the administrative restriction.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the director of the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Provenance
The Duke Chapel Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1948-2017.
Historical Note
History adopted from Duke Chapel website: http://www.chapel.duke.edu/home/.
When James B. Duke selected the site for Duke University's West Campus, in 1925, he chose to locate the Chapel on the site's highest ridge. The Chapel was the first building planned for the new campus, but the last one to be completed. Construction started in 1930, was completed in 1935, and cost nearly $2.3 million. The Chapel began to be used before its stained-glass windows and other details were finished; commencement was held in the Chapel in 1932. The Chapel was officially dedicated in 1935.
The Chapel fulfills James B. Duke's desire that the building exert a profound influence on the lives of the young women and men who attend the University. Duke Chapel is a nationally recognized pulpit, an acclaimed center of sacred music, and a place of learning and interfaith cooperation. Duke University Chapel's ever-widening ministry includes worship through prayer, word, and music; service within the University and community; celebration through concerts, special services, and festivals; and learning seminars, study groups, and retreats. The day-to-day ministry of the Chapel is shared with a wide and diverse community: students, faculty, staff, and the community; tourists and travelers; and patients, their families, and caregivers. Chapel life encompasses a variety of groups including Religious Life, Friends of the Chapel, Congregation, and Student Ministry. Duke Chapel is also the site of various concerts, voice and organ recitals, choir and carillon programs, and vesper ensembles.
Collection Overview
Contains material pertaining to the operation and activities of the Duke University Chapel and ranges in date from 1920-[ongoing]. The records are arranged in six series: administrative records, carillon/carilloneur, exercise programs and bulletins, sermons, registers and logbooks, and general files.
The Administrative records contain material created and accumulated by the Chapel Development Officer as well as the records of various committees including Chapel renovation and organ. Carillon material includes program logbooks created by the University Carillonneur and a special carillon program in honor of Terry Sanford. The exercise programs series is composed of printed programs from various services and exercises held in the Chapel: Sunday Service of Worship, Elementary Service, Faculty Service, Service for Elected Officials, various recitals, and Easter, Lenten, and Christmas services. The sermons series contains transcripts of sermons performed in the Chapel by various ministers, faculty, and guests of the University including William H. Willimon, James T. Cleland, Howard C. Wilkinson, and Waldo Beach. Registers and logbooks contains oversize bound volumes documenting Chapel attendance and weddings, baptisms, and funerals held in the Chapel. General files primarily consists of reference material used by Chapel staff: informal histories, information about chapel windows and exterior sculpture, informal patron inquiries, and various printed material. Major subjects include building and grounds, organ (Flentrop and Aeolian), tower and elevator, Chapel policies, weddings, and Chapel photo albums. Also present in the collection are programs for special services held in the Chapel observing V-E and V-J Days and the Chapel's dedication ceremony in 1935.
Separated Material
Subject files have been removed to form the Chapel Reference Collection, April 2007. "200 Bells for 200 Years" material (A94-73), Service for Elected Officials (A75-13), "Chapel Choir China Tour" videocassette (A97-6), Development Campaign material (A81-117), William Blackburn letter concerning Chapel windows (A78-139), and Brombaugh Organ Dedication (A97-81) were also incorporated into the Chapel Reference Collection.
Religious Life Staff records (A93-133), "The Weekday Chapel," a speech given by Chapel Hostess Marjorie Jones (A83-44), Stonecarving material (A84-79), and obituary of Elizabeth Lucinda Gotham (A82-68) were moved to Small Collections.
Sound recordings of sermons were moved to Chapel Sermons, 1954-2002 [sound recordings] collection.
Accessioned videocassettes "Chapel Tour" (A88-0029), Christmas Eve Service and Service for Elected Officials (A79-17), and "The Organs of Duke Chapel," were moved to the record and tape shelf.
Accessioned audio recordings Easter Broadcasts (A79-82), "Messiah," 1992 (A94-28), organ performances by David Arcus, 1997 (A98-76), ten 78rpm disc recordings of the Duke Summer School Choir from 1937-1941 (A80-62) were moved to the record and tape shelf.
Related Material
Chapel Reference Collection, 1933-ongoing
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Friends of Duke Chapel Records, 1973-1999
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Minister to the University (Dean of the Chapel) Records, 1940-1984
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chapel Sermons, 1954-2002 [sound recording]
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul S. Robinson Papers, 1932-1941
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James T. Cleland Papers, 1928-1975
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Memorial Records, 1929-1936
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Horace Trumbauer Architectural Drawings Collection, 1924-1958
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Waldo Beach Papers, 1949-1986
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Facilities Management Department Records, 1990-2006
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Universities and colleges -- Sermons; Sound recordings; Sermons; Chapels -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University. Chapel -- Organs; Duke University -- Buildings; Duke University -- Religious activities; Cleland, James T. (James Tough), 1903-; Beach, Waldo; Willimon, William H., 1946-; Duke University. Chapel -- Fund raising; Duke University. Divinity School
- Administrative Files, 1949-1991, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  The Administrative records contain material created and accumulated by the Chapel Development Officer as well as the records of various committees. Major subjects include Chapel Renovation Fund, Altar Guild, College of Bishops, and Chapel Renovation and Front Organ Committees.
  - Development Campaign, 1949-1991 (Box 1)
  - Development Campaign, 1957, 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Altar Guild, 1971-1982, undated (Box 1)
  - Altar Guild, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Renovation Fund, 1967-1977, 1984 (Box 1)
  - College of Bishops, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Renovation Committee, organ, 1965-1976 (Box 1)
  - Front Organ Committee, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Front Organ Committee, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Front Organ Committee, printed material, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
- Exercise Programs and Bulletins, 1932-2019
  The Chapel exercise programs and bulletins series is composed of printed programs from various services and exercises held in the Chapel: Sunday Service of Worship, Elementary Service, Faculty Service, various recitals, and Easter, Lenten, and Christmas services.
  - Chapel Dedication, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Gifts to Duke University Chapel, 1934-1978, undated (Box 46)
  - Carillon, Organ, and Worship Programs, 1938-1939 (Box 46)
  - Recital and Sunday Service Programs, 1939-1940 (Box 46)
  - Service of Worship, 1932-1955; 20 folders (Box 1)
  - Service of Worship, 1956-1977; 22 folders (Box 2)
  - Service of Worship, 1978-1996; 20 folders (Box 16)
  - Service of Worship, 1997-2004; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Service of Worship digital files, 2005; 105 desktop publishing and document files (PageMaker and PDF formats); approximately 200 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA17-01-0001-SET-0001)
  - Service of Worship, 2006-2009; 7 folders (Box 17)
  - Service of Worshop digital files, 2006; 37 document files (PDF format); approximately 10 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA17-01-0001-SET-0001)
  - Service of Worship, 2009-2010; 11 folders (Box 29)
  - Service of Worship, 2011; 12 folders (Box 30)
  - Service of Worship and Resurrection: Mary Duke Biddle Trent Semans, January 30, 2012; 1 folders (Box 29)
  - Service of Worship, January - August 2012; 9 folders (Box 30)
  - Service of Worship, September - December 2012; 5 folders (Box 31)
  - Service of Worship, 2013; 14 folders (Box 31)
  - Choral Vespers, 2014 (Box 31)
  - Service of Worship, January - June 1, 2014 (Box 31)
  - Service of Worship, June - December 2014 (Box 32)
  - Service of Worship digital files, 2015; 28 document files (PDF format); approximately 15 megabytes. (Digital-materials UA17-01-0001-SET-0001)
  - Service of Worship, May 3 - December 27, 2015; 4 folders (Box 32)
  - Service of Worship, January 3 - June 5, 2016; 3 folders (Box 32)
  - Service of Worship, June 2016 - April 2018; 4 folders (Box 32)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a program for the memorial service for H. Keith Brodie on December 05, 2016.
  - Service of Worship, 2017 September 20 (Box 48)
    Includes program for Honoring the Service of Duke Life Flight memorial for Mary Bartlett, Jeff Burke, Kristopher Harrison, and Crystal Sollinger.
  - Service of Worship, May 2018 - December 2019; 21 folders (Box 48)
    Includes Service of Holy Communion with the Rite of Ordination, 2018 April 5; and memorial services for Brenda E. Armstrong, M.D.; James Duke Biddle Trent Semans; Ronald L. Wilson; A Service of Thanksgiving and Rememberance for Duke Alumni; Elizabeth Bartlett Humphries; Onyekwere Emmanuel Akwari; Philip J. Herr; and, Peter James McCurdy.
  - Other than 11AM Sunday (3 folders), 1992-2002 (Box 29)
  - Recitals (other than organ), 1933-1999 (Box 29)
  - Organ Recitals (5 folders), 1932-1967 (Box 29)
  - Organ Recitals, 1968-2002, bulk 1968-1977 (Box 29)
  - Elementary Worship (2 folders), 1984-1985 (Box 29)
  - Elementary Worship, 1988-1990 (Box 29)
  - Elementary Worship, 1992 (Box 29)
  - Elementary Worship (2 folders), 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Elementary Worship, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - Bound Programs, September 1971-August 1972 (Box 4)
- Sermons, 1937-2002
  The sermons series contains transcripts of sermons performed in the Chapel by various ministers, faculty, and guests of the University. Notable speakers include William H. Willimon, James T. Cleland, Howard C. Wilkinson, and Waldo Beach.
  - Sermons, 1937-1941 (Box 4)
  - Sermons, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Sermons, 1947, 1949 (Box 4)
  - Sermons, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Sermons, 1952, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Sermons (13 folders), 1957-1968 (Box 4)
  - Sermons (24 folders), 1969-1982 (Box 5)
  - Sermons (21 folders), 1983-2002 (Box 6)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 6)
- Carillon/Carillonneur, 1966-2003
  Carillon material includes program logbooks created by the Chapel carillonneur, 1966-1973 and 1982-2002. Logs from 1974-1981 are absent. Also present is a special carillon program in honor of Terry Sanford and an encapsulated program from a special Service in Observance of V-J Day, August 1945.
  - Recital log, 1966-1973 (Box 7)
  - Recital logs (spiral bound notebooks), 1982-2012 (Box 7)
  - Music for the Obsequies of Terry Sanford, circa 1998 (Box 7)
  - Program for Service in Observance of V-J Day, August 1945 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Registers and Logbooks, 1920-2004
  Bound registers and logbooks that document Chapel attendance (a required component of student curriculum in the 1920s) as well as weddings, baptisms, and funerals held in the Chapel.
  - Student Chapel Attendance (2 bound logbooks), 1920-1921 (Box 8)
  - Student Chapel Attendance (3 bound logbooks), 1923-1925 (Box 9)
  - Marriage Registry, 1932-1979 (Box 10)
  - Baptismal Registry, 1933-1979 (Box 10)
  - Marriage and Baptismal Registry (microfilm), 1932-1979 (Box 10)
  - Register of Marriages, Baptisms, and Funerals, 1979-2004 (Box 11)
  - Chapel Register, Volume I, 1932-1933 (Box 12)
  - Chapel Register, Volume II, 1933-1934 (Box 13)
  - Chapel Register, Volume III, 1934-1935 (Box 14)
  - Chapel register volume 4, 1935 August - 1936 August (Box 33)
  - Chapel Register volume 5, 1936 October - 1937 October (Box 34)
  - Chapel Register volume 6, October 1937 - October 1937 - September 1938 (Box 35)
  - Chapel Register volume 7, 1938 November - 1939 July (Box 36)
  - Chapel Register volume 8, 1939 July - 1940 April (Box 37)
  - Chapel Register volume 9, 1940 April - December (Box 38)
  - Chapel Register volume 11, 1941 August - 1942 April (Box 39)
  - Chapel Register volume 12, 1942 April - 1943 August (Box 40)
  - Chapel Register volume 13, 1943 August - 1944 May (Box 41)
  - Chapel Register volume 14, 1944 May - 1945 March (Box 42)
  - Chapel Register volume 17, 1946 May - 1946 November (Box 43)
  - Wedding Programs, 2005-2007 (Box 44)
  - Wedding Programs, 2007-2008 (Box 45)
- General Files, 1933-2004
  General files primarily consists of reference material used by Chapel staff: informal histories, information about chapel windows and exterior sculpture, informal patron inquiries, and various printed material including bound publications, informational brochures, periodicals, and newspaper clippings. Also included in this series are Chapel photo albums. Major subjects include building and grounds, organ (Flentrop and Aeolian), tower and elevator, weddings, and Chapel policies.
  - Buildings and Grounds, 1997-2001 (Box 15)
  - Organs, Aeolian Holtkamp, 1977-1981, 1996 (Box 15)
  - Organs, Flentrop, 1976-1981 (Box 15)
  - Statistics, 1966-1983, 1991-1992 (Box 15)
  - Chapel Policies, 2000, undated (Box 15)
  - Christmas, 1996-2000 (Box 15)
  - Elevator and Tower, 1996-1999, undated (Box 15)
  - Duke Information, 1933-2003, undated (Box 15)
  - Duke Information, Duke Endowment (bound), undated (Box 15)
  - Cathedrals and Chapels, undated (Box 15)
  - Duke Police, (tower/tourists/keys), 1998 (Box 15)
  - Flowers, 1997-2001 (Box 15)
  - Kilgo, Bishop J.C., undated (Box 15)
  - Borrowed equipment log, 1975-1992 (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1966-1985 (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1990-1997 (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1998-1999 (Box 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2000-2003, undated (Box 15)
  - Newsletters, 1998-2004 (Box 15)
  - Service programs, 1945-2002 (Box 15)
  - Magazines, 1994, 1998, undated (Box 15)
  - Informational booklets (2 folders), undated (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - "Stones, Bricks, and Faces," by Marguerite Schumann, 1976 (Box 15)
  - "Spire and Spirit," by Alice Phillips, 1974 (Box 15)
  - "The Architecture of Duke University," by William Blackburn, 1946 (Box 15)
  - "The Windows of the Chapel," by Alice Phillips, undated (Box 15)
  - "The Flentrop Organ Dedicated in Memory of Benjamin N. Duke," 1976 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous reference, 1964-1980, 1992-2004 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous reference, undated (Box 15)
  - Copies, 1989-2007 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Duke Information, 2004-2009, undated (Box 18)
  - The Architecture of Duke University, 1946 (Box 18)
  - Christmas Miscellaneous, 1998-2007, undated (Box 18)
  - Christmas, 2001 (Box 18)
  - Christmas, 2003 (Box 18)
  - Christmas, 2004 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Chapel Information, 1993-2009 (Box 18)
  - Old Wedding Information (2 folders), 1970-1996, undated (Box 18)
  - Weddings Miscellaneous, 2005-2007, undated (Box 18)
  - Wedding Booklets (2 folders), 1995-2005, undated (Box 18)
  - Seventy Five Years of Weddings, 2008 (Box 18)
  - Clippings, 1980-2007, undated (Box 18)
  - Album, 1933-1959 (Box 19)
  - Album, 1960-1979 (Box 20)
  - Album, 1980-1999 (Box 21)
  - Album, 2000-2006 (Box 22)
  - Album, 2007-2008 (Box 23)
- Ministers, Committes, Subject Files (Accession UA2012.0018), 1980-2007
  General files primarily consists of correspondence and documentation pertaining to Chapel ministers and committees.
  - Brueggemann, Dr. Walter (Box 24)
  - Coakley, Sarah (Box 24)
  - Copeland, Jennifer (Box 24)
  - Davis, Ellen (Box 24)
  - Ferree, Rev. Nancy (Box 24)
  - Finnin, The Rev. Dr. Will (Box 24)
  - Forbes, Rev. Dr. James A. (Box 24)
  - Gilbert, The Rev. Dr. Paula E. (Box 24)
  - Gomes, The Rev. Dr. Peter (2 Folders) (Box 24)
  - Harvard, Rev. Joseph III (Box 24)
  - Hays, Professor Richard B. (Box 24)
  - Hillerbrand, The Rev. Dr. Hans (Box 24)
  - Hodges_Copple, Ann (Box 24)
  - Howell, James C. (Box 24)
  - Jenkins, David O. (Oli) (Box 24)
  - Jones, Bishop L. Bevel (Box 24)
  - Jones, The Rev. Susan (Box 24)
  - Jones, Gregory (Box 24)
  - Kammerer, Charlene (Box 24)
  - Langford, Andrew (Box 24)
  - Lawrence, The Rev. William B. (Box 24)
  - Lischer, Dr. Richard (2 Folders) (Box 24)
  - Long, The Rev. Dr. Thomas G. (Box 24)
  - Lundblad, The Reverend Barbara (Box 24)
  - Myers, Ched (Box 24)
  - Noren, Carol Marie (Box 24)
  - Proctor, The Rev. Dr. Samuel D. (Box 24)
  - Quash, Ben (Box 24)
  - Quick, Dr. William (Box 24)
  - Reifsnyder, Richard (Box 24)
  - Rutledge, The Rev. Fleming (Box 24)
  - Sager, Rabbi Steven (Box 24)
  - Salmon-Campbell, The Reverend Joan (Box 24)
  - Seamans, Mrs. Mary (Box 24)
  - Smith, Charles M. (Box 24)
  - Smith, The Rev. Dr. D. Moody (Box 24)
  - Stockton, Thomas B. (Box 24)
  - Storey, Peter J. (Box 24)
  - Taylor, The Rev. Barbara B. (Box 24)
  - Taylor, Rev. Dr. Gardner (Box 24)
  - Turner, William C. (Box 24)
  - Walrond, The Rev. Michael (Box 24)
  - Ward, Hope Morgan (Box 24)
  - Warlick, The Rev. Dr. Harold (Box 24)
  - Warner, Lacey (Box 24)
  - Willimon, Reverend William (Box 24)
  - Wilson, Gerald (Box 24)
  - Young, Frances (2 Folders) (Box 24)
  - Zondervan (Box 24)
  - Photos: Sam (Box 24)
  - Campus Culture Initiative (Box 24)
  - University History and Talks (Box 24)
  - Baccalaureate Details, 2006 (Box 24)
  - Internet Working Group, 2007 (Box 24)
  - Dean's Course, 2009 (Box 24)
  - Center for Reconcilliation (Box 24)
  - Kenan Institute, 2005-2010 (Box 24)
  - Race Relations Subcommittee, 2006 (Box 24)
  - Jones, Greg, circa 2006 (Box 24)
  - Visitor Statistics, 1995-2005 (Box 24)
  - Campus Life and Learning Project Report, 2006 (Box 25)
  - Misc Minutes, Correspondence, and Documentation (4 Folders) (Box 25)
  - Misc Minutes, Correspondence, and Documentation (2 Folders) (Box 26)
  - Linens and Alter Pieces (Box 26)
  - Scrapbook Clippings and Misc (Box 26)
  - Stations of the Cross Programs (Box 26)
  - Dean Weiss Recommendations, 2005 (Box 26)
  - Same Sex Unions Documentation (Box 26)
  - 75th Anniversary of Weddings, 2008 (Box 26)
- The Congregation at Duke Chapel Newsletter, 1987-2017; 2 boxes
  - 1987 Jan.-Dec. (except April, May) (Box 27)
  - 1988 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1989 Jan.-Dec. (except Aug.) (Box 27)
  - 1990 Jan.-Dec. (except Feb.) (Box 27)
  - 1991 Jan.-Dec. (except Sept.) (Box 27)
  - 1992 Jan.-Dec. (except Feb., May) (Box 27)
  - 1993 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1994 Jan.-Dec. (except Feb.) (Box 27)
  - 1995 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1996 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1997 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1998 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 1999 Jan.-Dec. (Box 27)
  - 2000 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2001 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2002 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2003 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2004 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2005 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2006 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2007 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2008 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2009 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2010 Jan.-Dec. (Box 28)
  - 2011 January-December (Box 47)
  - 2012 January-December (Box 47)
  - 2012 January-December (Box 47)
  - 2014 January-December (Box 47)
  - 2015 January-December (Box 47)
  - 2016 January-December (Box 47)
  - 2017 January-March (Box 47)